Difficulty of raising an 8th grader
with intellectual disability
Nice to meet you.
Thank you for your teachings.
My son is an 8th grader.
He has an intellectual disability.
I have started to do
morning prayers
at 5 am for over
a month now.
I would like to receive a
prayer script from you.
How old is your child?
(Questioner)
He is 15 years old.
Do you want a prayer script
for your child?
Or, do you want
one for yourself?
Since I started it
because of my son
I would like to pray for him
And to find peace
within myself also.
Is it difficult raising your son?
(Questioner)
A little..
Why is it difficult?
Comparing your son
with a disability to a puppy
Who is better at
caring for himself?
(Questioner)
My child is.
People who raise puppies
don't complain
But you are
having difficulty?
Nobody complains that
raising a puppy is hard work.
Nobody has ever asked me
"I am having difficulties raising a
puppy. What shall I do?"
(Audience Laugher)
Even with the disability
Your son's IQ must be
higher than a puppy.
What do you think?
(Questioner)
Yes, I agree.
So, why is it hard then?
Doesn't your son take
better care of himself
than an infant?
(Questioner)
Yes, he does
You raised an infant well,
didn't you?
So, what is the problem?
(Questioner) I thought he was a bit
slow when he was young
(Questioner) But I didn't know that
he had this disability
(Questioner) But as he grew older...
So, I can understand
the difficulty
when you didn't know
that he had a disability
But now you know
It's good that
he is not worse
(Questioner) That's true.
That is why I started to pray
What is there to pray about
with this sort of thing?
Accept that he
has this disability.
But he is smarter
than a dog.
What's is there to pray about?
Sometimes, he acts out these days.
Maybe because he is a teenager
Of course, he does that.
He is intellectually handicapped
not physically.
He is normal physically
so it's to be expected.
So?
I want to pray every morning
with the prayer script you give.
So, recite this
"Thank you dear Buddha.
My son has this disability
but he is better than a dog."
Pray with this thought
Countless people
raise puppies
Then, there are facilities where
the children with disabilities are
cared for, aren't there?
(Sunim) Children with physical
disabilities, mental disabilities
I know there are
Who has the worse job?
Someone who cares
for many such children
or you who care for only one?
(Questioner) Of course, it's harder for
someone who cares for many.
I am sure it is hard
for that person
But she/he doesn't
cry over it like you.
(Questioner)
I wasn't going to cry but...
How is it then
The person there
doesn't ask about
"How to care for the children?"
Nobody ever asks me
for a prayer script.
(Sunim) Why?
What is the difference?
If we have to say it
For them,
the kids are not their own.
But for you,
it's your own child.
Then it should be hard for them
but not for you.
He is your own child.
But how does this occur?
Only one difference
That person gets paid
and you don't.
Isn't it?
That person gets paid to care
for the children while you don't
So, in some way,
it's about money.
(Laughter)
You may think, that person gets paid
but how come I don't
No, Sunim. It is absolutely
not like that
(Sunim) In that case
You have no reason
to cry or be sad.
Especially, the nuns
who take care of children
They don't even get paid.
They do the work without any pay
In general, the
professionals are paid
To take care of the
disabled children.
But, in the past, the nuns
who took care of those children
Did not get paid.
They did it for free
throughout their lives.
Even though the kids were
not their own.
We call them angels,
don't we?
But you have only one child
and your own.
(Sunimi) Why do you tear up
caring for your own child.
(Sunim) Why is it
so hard for you?
(Questioner)
You are right.
Think of it this way
If you owe a debt,
that would be a disaster
If you're having a
hard time paying back
You'd have to pray or not?
But if somebody pays you
$1,000 every day
Would you find this hard?
Would there be anyone asking
me for a prayer script for this?
When you owe $1,000,
you'd ask for a prayer script.
But nobody asks for a prayer script
when it is given to them.
The problem arises out of
you wanting something.
When you look at
your child as a problem
He becomes a problem.
He will have hard time
living this life as a happy person.
As his parent, you ought to
look at him as a blessing.
Then living with him
will be joyful.
If you consider raising a
puppy as a disaster
how can you be happy?
You'd have to
feed a puppy, right?
give it a bath, no?
But you are happy
doing these things
So, raising a puppy
is a blessing
I myself don't understand
why people do these things.
It costs money, time and energy.
What is it for?
But they are crazy
about the puppies
And this becomes a
source of happiness.
These things are
done for dogs.
But for you,
it's your own child.
He is your child,
smarter than a puppy.
Why is it so hard for you?
If you consider caring for
your child is a blessing
You would not need a
prayer script or anything else.
You don't consider
this as a blessing
You think this is a curse.
If you don't change
your point of view
And change negative thinking
about this
As I mentioned before,
you can pray all you want
But if you look at him with
this negative point of view
No prayer will help.
You have to change your mind.
Look at it positively.
Don't think of this as
a negative thing.
Think of it as a blessing,
as a good fortune.
If you were a Christian,
taking care of him well
Will have you a seat reserved
in heaven, or no?
It will be a done deal
for you to reach nirvana.
Why don't you want to do the thing
that will get you to heaven?
Why would to head to
hell instead?
Accept this as a blessing.
If he were physically well
and a good student
He will be loved
even by neighbors.
But the neighbors
don't care for kids
With mental and
physical handicap.
He will not be liked, right?
But a mother loves
and takes care of him.
(Sunim) So, the nuns evoke
mothers' hearts.
But you are acting like a woman
in the neighborhood.
That is why it is hard for you.
Try to activate a mother's heart.
(Questioner)
Yes, I understand.
Nothing to cry about,
pray about.
Get in touch with a
mother's heart.
This is Bodhisattva!
Accept this as a blessing.
(Applause)
But you only look at
your child as a problem.
You can't see this
as a blessing .
See this as a blessing,
your life will change.
As long as you
see this as a problem
You will suffer and your child
will not turn out well, either.
Why? His mom thinks of him
as a problem.
How can he turn out well?
Even when the whole world
calls him a problem
His mom should think of him
as blessing.
Remember Helen Keller.
She couldn't see, hear, or speak
But her mother
thought of her as a blessing
And took real good
care of her.
She became better than anyone
who could see, hear and speak.
Most people think
of this as a curse.
His mom also thinks
of this a curse.
(Sunim) So how can he
turn out to be happy?